Edward L. Bernays Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Part III: Client, Institution, and Organization File, 1913-1992 (Box III:26-40)
  - United Fruit Co.
    - General, 1950
    - Guatemala and Honduras
      - 1950-1953
      - 1954
        - Mar.-June, (2 folders)
        - July-Dec., (3 folders) (Box III:38)
      - 1955-1957, (8 folders)
      - 1958, 1976-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box III:39)
  - United States Information Agency, 1955-1976, undated, (2 folders)
  - University of Wisconsin, School of Journalism, Madison, Wis., 1955-1958
  - Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York, N.Y., 1923, undated
  - West Valley College, Campbell, Calif., 1968
  - Worker-management study
    - 1941
      - June, (2 folders)
      - July-Nov. (Box III:40)
  - World Health Foundation, undated
- Part III: Subject File, 1919-1994 (Box III:40-56)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, background information, notes, interviews, press releases, photographs, lists, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  - Addresses, 1977, 1992, undated, (2 folders) (Box III:40)
  - Advertising for Bernays's office, 1945-1946, undated
  - Aging, 1981-1991, undated
  - Art, 1965-1975, undated (Box III:41)
  - Birthdays
    - Seventieth, 1961-1962, (5 folders)
    - Seventy-fifth, 1966-1967
    - Eightieth, 1971-1972, (6 folders)
    - Eighty-third, 1975 (Box III:42)
    - Ninetieth, 1981-1982, (5 folders)
    - Ninety-second, 1983
    - Ninety-fourth, 1985, undated, (2 folders)
    - Ninety-fifth, 1986-1987, (3 folders)
    - Ninety-sixth, 1987
    - Ninety-nineth, 1990 (Box III:43)
    - One hundredth, 1991
  - Boston University, Boston, Mass., 1962-1985, undated, (4 folders)
  - Childs, Harwood L., 1934-1935
  - Cigarette smoking, 1962-1964, 1975, 1983, undated
  - Committees and organizations (Box III:44)
    - Citizens' Emergency Committee to Save Memorial Drive, Cambridge, Mass.
      - Background material, 1923, 1961-1965, undated, (2 folders)
      - Correspondence, 1960-1965, undated, (4 folders)
      - General, 1962-1965, undated
      - Press, 1963-1965, undated
      - Statements, 1964-1965, undated
    - Emergency Committee for a Reappraisal of United States Overseas Information Policies and Programs, 1969-1970
    - General, 1925-1931, 1947, 1961-1990, undated (Box III:45)
  - Condolences re Doris Fleischman Bernays's death, 1980-1981, (5 folders)
  - Credit expansion and recovery, 1931-1936, undated
  - Creel, George, 1964, undated
  - Crime, 1964, 1970-1975, undated (Box III:46)
  - Darlington, Helen, 1944-1945
  - Disarmament action network media project, 1986
  - Edward L. Bernays' Foundation
    - Anglo-American international relations contest
      - Award winners
        - General, 1967-1968, undated
        - Luncheon, 1967-1968
      - Clippings, 1966-1968, undated, (3 folders)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1966-1968, (4 folders)
        - United Kingdom press, 1967-1968, (3 folders) (Box III:47)
        - United States press and organizations, 1966-1968, (3 folders)
      - General, 1966-1968, undated, (2 folders)
      - Luncheon, 1966-1967
      - Press releases, 1966-1968, undated
      - Watson, Cowan, 1968
    - Economic justice for homemakers program, 1977-1979, undated (Box III:48)
    - General, 1964-1985, undated, (2 folders)
    - Lecture series
      - Edward R. Murrow Center of Public Diplomacy, Medford, Mass., 1965-1973, undated, (3 folders)
      - Freedom of expression lectures, 1971, (2 folders)
      - General, 1963-1971, undated, (4 folders) (Box III:49)
    - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, 1973-1977
  - Event planning, 1952
  - Galard-Terraube, Genevieve de, 1954, 1967
  - Hale and Dorr, 1962-1963
  - Harold Ober Associates, 1964-1965
  - Information, 1925-1929
  - Institute of Public Relations, London, England, 1957, 1966, undated
  - Interviews
    - 1956-1970
    - 1971-1991, undated, (5 folders) (Box III:50)
  - Jones, Ernest, 1957
  - Library of Congress, 1964-1970, (2 folders)
  - Lists
    - 1919, 1925, 1931-1936, 1949-1962
    - 1963-1983, undated, (5 folders) (Box III:51)
  - Massachusetts prosperity program, 1989-1990
  - NAACP, 1964-1965, 1973, 1980
  - Pharmaceutical profession, 1943, undated
  - Promotion samples
    - 1943-1944, 1958
    - 1959, undated (Box III:52)
  - Propaganda, 1928-1931, 1938, 1944, 1970-1971, undated
  - Public relations
    - Associations, national, 1970-1977, undated, (2 folders)
    - Card file (Box III:53)
    - General, 1935-1938, 1947, 1964-1969, 1975-1980, 1990, undated, (5 folders) (Box III:54)
    - Licenses for practitioners, 1947, 1974-1993, undated, (2 folders)
    - Notes, 1955, undated
    - Printed matter
      - 1922-1932, 1941-1946, 1960-1968
      - 1975-1994, undated (Box III:55)
  - Rank, Otto, 1923-1924
  - Rieber, Torkild, 1941
  - Schedules and itineraries, 1984-1989, undated
  - Sullivan, Mark, 1932
  - Travel
    - Europe, 1949, 1957, 1966, (4 folders)
    - Puerto Rico, 1984
  - United Nations, 1964
  - United States, image abroad
    - 1968
      - Apr.-June
      - July
        - 2-10
        - 11-23 (Box III:56)
    - 1969-1970, undated
  - Vietnam Conflict, 1962-1972
  - Vondra, Joan, 1988-1992
  - Wedding anniversary, fiftieth, 1972
- Part III: Speeches and Writings File, 1912-1992 (Box III:56-74)
  Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, articles, book drafts, book reviews, editorials, forewords and introductions, newsletters, pamphlets, background material, notes, bibliographies, outlines, poetry, announcements and programs, evaluations, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically. Arranged alphabetically into two categories, writings by Bernays and writings by others, which are further arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Speech file (Box III:56)
    - Announcements and programs, 1923-1953, 1961-1992, undated, (8 folders)
    - Evaluations, 1985-1987
    - Miscellany, 1935, 1961, 1981-1987, undated (Box III:57)
    - Press, 1933-1992, undated, (5 folders)
    - Texts and related material
      - 1925-1929, 1936-1964, (7 folders)
      - 1965-1980, (8 folders) (Box III:58)
      - 1981-1990, (2 folders) (Box III:59)
      - Undated, (6 folders); (1 folder) (Box III:60)
  - Writings
    - By Bernays
      - Articles and related material
        - 1912-1946, (9 folders)
        - 1947-1992, (9 folders) (Box III:61)
        - Undated, (5 folders) (Box III:62)
      - Book reviews, 1926, 1951-1989, undated, (3 folders)
      - Books
        - Biography of an Idea: Memoirs of Public Relations Counsel Edward L. Bernays (1965)
          - Advertising and promotion, 1964-1966, undated, (2 folders)
          - Background material, 1916, 1923, 1929-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box III:63)
          - Correspondence
            - 1949, 1957-1964, (2 folders)
            - 1965
              - Jan.-Oct., (4 folders)
              - Nov.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box III:64)
            - 1966, 1988, undated, (3 folders)
          - General, 1965, undated, (2 folders)
          - Outlines, 1963, undated (Box III:65)
          - Permissions, 1964, undated, (4 folders)
          - Reviews, 1965-1967
          - Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1963-1968, undated, (3 folders)
          - Various drafts, undated, (8 folders); (6 folders) (Box III:66, Box III:67)
        - Broadway Anthology (1917), 1917-1918, undated
        - Case for Reappraisal of U.S. Overseas Information Policies and Programs (1970), 1970-1971
        - Crystalizing Public Opinion (1924), 1924, 1961-1962, undated
        - Engineering of Consent (1955), 1955-1956, 1963, 1970, 1986, undated
        - "I Take My Pen in Hand" (unpublished), undated
        - Later Years: Public Relations Insights, 1956-1986 (1986), 1987, undated
        - Outline of Careers: A Practical Guide to Achievement (1927), 1927-1929 (Box III:68)
        - Propaganda (1928), 1928-1929, undated
        - Proposed, 1938, undated
        - Public Relations (1952), 1952, 1965-1966, 1978-1984, undated, (2 folders)
        - "Public Relations Counsel: A Personal History" (unpublished), undated
        - Speak Up for Democracy (1940), 1938-1941, undated
        - Take Your Place at the Peace Table (1945), 1945, undated
        - Untitled manuscripts, undated, (4 folders)
        - Your Future in a Public Relations Career (1979) (Box III:69)
          - Draft, undated
          - General, 1977-1980, undated
        - Your Future in Public Relations (1961), 1961-1962, 1969
      - Editorials for the Dietetic and Hygienic Gazette, 1913
      - Forewords and introductions, 1934, 1965, undated
      - Letters to editors, 1920, 1940-1986, undated, (5 folders)
      - Lists, 1948-1951, undated
      - Miscellany, 1927, 1964-1971, 1978-1979, undated, (3 folders)
      - Newsletters (Box III:70)
        - Contact
          - Correspondence (bound)
            - 1922-1932, (2 folders)
            - 1925-1936, (2 folders) (Box III:71)
            - 1935 (Box III:72)
          - Texts, undated
        - Untitled, undated
      - Notes, 1970, 1984, undated
      - Pamphlets
        - Future of Private Enterprise, correspondence, 1942-1943
          - A-F
          - G-Z, (6 folders) (Box III:73)
        - Universities-Pathfinders in Public Opinion, 1936-1938, (2 folders)
      - Poetry, 1925, undated
      - Volume of writings, 1920-1942, undated
      - Fragments, undated (Box III:74)
    - By others
      - Bibliographies of Bernays's writings
        - 1957 edition, 1955-1958
        - 1978 edition
          - Correspondence, 1976-1979
          - General, undated
          - Press, 1977-1979
      - General, 1926-1937, 1945, 1961, 1967, 1976, 1982-1987, undated, (2 folders)
- Part III: Miscellany, 1777-1993 (Box III:74-77)
  Correspondence, financial and legal papers, certificates, collected items, broadsides, pamphlets, sketches, scrapbooks, biographical material, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Awards and honors (Box III:74)
    - 1925-1926, 1941-1954, 1960-1990, (5 folders)
    - 1991-1993, undated, (3 folders) (Box III:75)
  - Biographical file, 1931-1938, 1956-1965, 1971-1993, undated, (3 folders)
  - Citizenship papers, 1946-1947
  - Financial and legal papers, 1903, 1925-1938, 1948-1966, 1980, 1990-1991, (3 folders)
  - Manuscript and pamphlet collection, 1777, 1797, 1833, 1861-1865, 1885-1886, 1942, undated (Box III:76)
  - Miscellany, 1911, 1918-1923, 1930, 1942-1947, 1954, 1964-1970, 1980-1988, undated, (2 folders)
  - Printed matter
    - 1913-1976, (6 folders)
    - 1977-1992, undated, (8 folders) (Box III:77)
  - Sketches, undated
- Part III: Oversize, 1916-1966 (Box III:OV 1-30)
  Removed and organized and described separately. Arranged alphabetically into two categories, client, institution, and organization, and personal. The client scrapbooks are further arranged alphabetically by subject and the personal scrapbooks chronologically.
  - Scrapbooks (Box III:OV 1)
    - Client, institution, and organization file
      - Gelatin
        - 1924, undated
        - 1925-1926, undated (Box III:OV 2)
      - Retail Millinery Association (Box III:OV 3)
        - 1925
          - Jan.-Feb.
          - Jan.-Mar (Box III:OV 4)
          - Feb., (4 vols.) (Box III:OV 5-OV 8)
          - Feb.-Mar. (Box III:OV 9)
          - Mar., (3 vols.) (Box III:OV 10-OV 12)
          - Mar-Apr. (Box III:OV 13)
      - Velvet Fashion Service Bureau (Box III:OV 14)
        - 1925
          - Mar.
          - Mar.-Apr., (2 vols.) (Box III:OV 15-OV 16)
          - Mar.-May (Box III:OV 17)
          - May-July (Box III:OV 18)
          - July (Box III:OV 19)
          - July-Aug. (Box III:OV 20)
          - Aug. (Box III:OV 21)
    - Personal (Box III:OV 22)
      - 1916-1922
      - 1917-1927 (Box III:OV 23)
      - 1927-1930 (Box III:OV 24)
      - 1952 (Box III:OV 25)
      - 1952-1953 (Box III:OV 26)
      - 1957-1958 (Box III:OV 27)
      - 1959-1960 (Box III:OV 28)
      - 1960-1961 (Box III:OV 29)
      - 1965-1966 (Box III:OV 30)